{
  "reference_number": "9163",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "A Clear statement of Government intent is the best way to ensure all sectors of society understand the commitment that needs to be\n made and the best way to ensure this is the main priority for future budget spending. Without a clear plan to avert climate change\n\n there is little point in focussing on other future social needs or priorities because will have a bleak and economically desperate future.\n due to the severe impact on our primary industries and land use."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The focus on emission reduction needs to be a comprehensive one."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should include a focus on the development of practical small and large scale carbon sequestration projects as well as emission\n\n reductions. Research and development of effective torrefaction systems (or even \"supertorrefaction systems; summarily the use of\n \"char\" processes, heating organic matter in anoxic conditions so as to create and sequester carbon using either existing stock/food\n crops or forestry including forestry slash and waste). There are significant opportunities for local primary producers and for export of\n\n expertise and technology in this field. Local small scale operations may be just as effective as industrial scale projects. Establishing an\n efficient industry in NZ will allow us to promote and encourage other first and third world countries. We have clear international\n obligations in this regard."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "This is a difficult decision because it may be necessary to act sooner, but we cannot risk delay and should strive to reach the target\n as early as possible regardless. Global warming must be kept below 2 degrees."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "They should form part of our overall fiscal imperitives. They are more important than any of the other targets the Reserve\n\n Bank/Treasury may have."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This is too difficult for me sorry. It really does depend on what will most effectively get us to goal zero as soon as possible."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As above."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Broadly, but there must be priority given to scientific knowledge over short o9r medium term economic co9ncerns. The biggest\neconomic concern we have is climat change."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Essential that we have transparency, focus and avoid ignorance of the goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Science. Science. Science. Work with all scientific disciplines including the social sciences, but vested self-interested groups cannot\nbe allowed undue influence. Data, statistics, facts, reason and logic must prevail here."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And it must be an august body with genuine Mana and influence. It's recommendations should not be ignored."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Mana and control please, Provided the commission has the right science dominated composition."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Broadly, yes, but Science first please."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Change is here, now."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please can we have the best cross-party consensus here but please can we be guided by science and objectivity and not by self\ninterest or short term economic concerns. We are all going to have to change. We are all going to have to make some sacrifices and\n\nsuffer some short term losses perhaps. if we are smart, swift and innovative we can actually profit substantially, both in terms of a\nhealthy safe future and a booming carbon negative economy. Yes, carbon negative. We can help ourselves and others here and we\n\nmust try."
    }
  ]
}
